[God is the Greatest]
[الله أكبر]
[1:2] Praise be to God, Lord of the worlds.
٢  الْحَمْدُ لِلَّهِ رَبِّ الْعَالَمِينَ
[1:3] The Almighty, the Merciful.
٣  الرَّحْمَٰنِ الرَّحِيمِ
[1:4] Sovereign of the Day of Recompense.
٤  مَالِكِ يَوْمِ الدِّينِ
[1:5] You alone we serve, and You alone we seek for help.
٥  إِيَّاكَ نَعْبُدُ وَإِيَّاكَ نَسْتَعِينُ
[1:6] Guide us to the straight path.
٦  اهْدِنَا الصِّرَاطَ الْمُسْتَقِيمَ
[1:7] The path of those You have blessed, not of those who have incurred the wrath, nor the misguided.
٧  صِرَاطَ الَّذِينَ أَنْعَمْتَ عَلَيْهِمْ غَيْرِ الْمَغْضُوبِ عَلَيْهِمْ وَلَا الضَّالِّينَ
[Amin]
آمِينَ
1. Kaf. Ha. Ya. `Ayn. Sad.
١  كهيعص
2. A reminder of the mercy of your Lord to His servant Zachariah.
٢  ذِكْرُ رَحْمَتِ رَبِّكَ عَبْدَهُ زَكَرِيَّا
3. When he called out to his Lord secretly.
٣  إِذْ نَادَىٰ رَبَّهُ نِدَاءً خَفِيًّا
4. He said: "My Lord, my bones have gone frail, and my hair has turned white, and I have never been mischievous in imploring You my Lord."
٤  قَالَ رَبِّ إِنِّي وَهَنَ الْعَظْمُ مِنِّي وَاشْتَعَلَ الرَّأْسُ شَيْبًا وَلَمْ أَكُنْ بِدُعَائِكَ رَبِّ شَقِيًّا
5. "And I fear the kinfolk after I am gone, and my wife is infertile, so grant me from Yourself an ally."
٥  وَإِنِّي خِفْتُ الْمَوَالِيَ مِنْ وَرَائِي وَكَانَتِ امْرَأَتِي عَاقِرًا فَهَبْ لِي مِنْ لَدُنْكَ وَلِيًّا
6. "To inherit from me, and inherit from the descendants of Jacob. And make him my Lord, well pleasing."
٦  يَرِثُنِي وَيَرِثُ مِنْ آلِ يَعْقُوبَ ۖ وَاجْعَلْهُ رَبِّ رَضِيًّا
7. "O Zachariah, We give you glad tidings of a son whose name is John. We have not given that name before to anyone."
٧  يَا زَكَرِيَّا إِنَّا نُبَشِّرُكَ بِغُلَامٍ اسْمُهُ يَحْيَىٰ لَمْ نَجْعَلْ لَهُ مِنْ قَبْلُ سَمِيًّا
8. He said: "My Lord, how can I have a son when my wife is infertile, and I have reached a very old age?"
٨  قَالَ رَبِّ أَنَّىٰ يَكُونُ لِي غُلَامٌ وَكَانَتِ امْرَأَتِي عَاقِرًا وَقَدْ بَلَغْتُ مِنَ الْكِبَرِ عِتِيًّا
9. He said: "It is such that your Lord has said. It is an easy thing for Me. And I had created you before, when you were not a thing."
٩  قَالَ كَذَٰلِكَ قَالَ رَبُّكَ هُوَ عَلَيَّ هَيِّنٌ وَقَدْ خَلَقْتُكَ مِنْ قَبْلُ وَلَمْ تَكُ شَيْئًا
10. He said: "My Lord, make for me a sign." He said: "Your sign is that you will not speak to the people for three nights consecutively."
١٠  قَالَ رَبِّ اجْعَلْ لِي آيَةً ۚ قَالَ آيَتُكَ أَلَّا تُكَلِّمَ النَّاسَ ثَلَاثَ لَيَالٍ سَوِيًّا
11. So he went out among his people from the temple enclosure, and he indicated to them that they should glorify Him at dawn and dusk.
١١  فَخَرَجَ عَلَىٰ قَوْمِهِ مِنَ الْمِحْرَابِ فَأَوْحَىٰ إِلَيْهِمْ أَنْ سَبِّحُوا بُكْرَةً وَعَشِيًّا
12. "O John, take the Book with confidence." And We gave him authority while in his youth.
١٢  يَا يَحْيَىٰ خُذِ الْكِتَابَ بِقُوَّةٍ ۖ وَآتَيْنَاهُ الْحُكْمَ صَبِيًّا
13. And tenderness from Us, and purity, and he was ever righteous.
١٣  وَحَنَانًا مِنْ لَدُنَّا وَزَكَاةً ۖ وَكَانَ تَقِيًّا
14. And dutiful to his parents, and never was he a disobedient tyrant.
١٤  وَبَرًّا بِوَالِدَيْهِ وَلَمْ يَكُنْ جَبَّارًا عَصِيًّا
15. And peace be upon him the day he was born, and the day he dies, and the Day he is resurrected alive.
١٥  وَسَلَامٌ عَلَيْهِ يَوْمَ وُلِدَ وَيَوْمَ يَمُوتُ وَيَوْمَ يُبْعَثُ حَيًّا
16. And relate in the Book, Mary, when she withdrew herself from her family to a place which was to the east.
١٦  وَاذْكُرْ فِي الْكِتَابِ مَرْيَمَ إِذِ انْتَبَذَتْ مِنْ أَهْلِهَا مَكَانًا شَرْقِيًّا
17. So she took a barrier to separate her from them, so We sent Our Spirit to her, and he took on the shape of a human being in all similarity.
١٧  فَاتَّخَذَتْ مِنْ دُونِهِمْ حِجَابًا فَأَرْسَلْنَا إِلَيْهَا رُوحَنَا فَتَمَثَّلَ لَهَا بَشَرًا سَوِيًّا
18. She said: "I seek refuge with the Almighty from you if you are righteous."
١٨  قَالَتْ إِنِّي أَعُوذُ بِالرَّحْمَٰنِ مِنْكَ إِنْ كُنْتَ تَقِيًّا
19. He said: "I am the messenger of your Lord, to grant you the gift of a pure son."
١٩  قَالَ إِنَّمَا أَنَا رَسُولُ رَبِّكِ لِأَهَبَ لَكِ غُلَامًا زَكِيًّا
20. She said: "How can I have a son when no human being has been with me, nor have I desired such?"
٢٠  قَالَتْ أَنَّىٰ يَكُونُ لِي غُلَامٌ وَلَمْ يَمْسَسْنِي بَشَرٌ وَلَمْ أَكُ بَغِيًّا
21. He said: "It is such that your Lord has said, it is easy for Me. And We shall make him a sign for the people and a mercy from Us. It is a matter already ordained."
٢١  قَالَ كَذَٰلِكِ قَالَ رَبُّكِ هُوَ عَلَيَّ هَيِّنٌ ۖ وَلِنَجْعَلَهُ آيَةً لِلنَّاسِ وَرَحْمَةً مِنَّا ۚ وَكَانَ أَمْرًا مَقْضِيًّا
22. So she was pregnant with him, and she went to deliver in a far place.
٢٢  فَحَمَلَتْهُ فَانْتَبَذَتْ بِهِ مَكَانًا قَصِيًّا
23. Then the birth pains came to her, by the trunk of a palm tree. She said: "I wish I had died before this, and became totally forgotten!"
٢٣  فَأَجَاءَهَا الْمَخَاضُ إِلَىٰ جِذْعِ النَّخْلَةِ قَالَتْ يَا لَيْتَنِي مِتُّ قَبْلَ هَٰذَا وَكُنْتُ نَسْيًا مَنْسِيًّا
24. But then he called to her from beneath her: "Do not be sad, your Lord has made below you a stream."
٢٤  فَنَادَاهَا مِنْ تَحْتِهَا أَلَّا تَحْزَنِي قَدْ جَعَلَ رَبُّكِ تَحْتَكِ سَرِيًّا
25. "And shake the trunk of this palm tree, it will cause ripe dates to fall upon you."
٢٥  وَهُزِّي إِلَيْكِ بِجِذْعِ النَّخْلَةِ تُسَاقِطْ عَلَيْكِ رُطَبًا جَنِيًّا
26. "So eat and drink and be content. If you see any human being, then say: 'I have vowed an abstinence for the Almighty, so I will not talk today to any of mankind.'"
٢٦  فَكُلِي وَاشْرَبِي وَقَرِّي عَيْنًا ۖ فَإِمَّا تَرَيِنَّ مِنَ الْبَشَرِ أَحَدًا فَقُولِي إِنِّي نَذَرْتُ لِلرَّحْمَٰنِ صَوْمًا فَلَنْ أُكَلِّمَ الْيَوْمَ إِنْسِيًّا
27. Then she came to her people carrying him. They said: "O Mary, you have come with a thing totally unexpected!"
٢٧  فَأَتَتْ بِهِ قَوْمَهَا تَحْمِلُهُ ۖ قَالُوا يَا مَرْيَمُ لَقَدْ جِئْتِ شَيْئًا فَرِيًّا
28. "O sister of Aaron, your father was not a wicked man, and your mother has never been unchaste!"
٢٨  يَا أُخْتَ هَارُونَ مَا كَانَ أَبُوكِ امْرَأَ سَوْءٍ وَمَا كَانَتْ أُمُّكِ بَغِيًّا
29. So she pointed to him. They said: "How can we talk to someone who is a child in a cradle?"
٢٩  فَأَشَارَتْ إِلَيْهِ ۖ قَالُوا كَيْفَ نُكَلِّمُ مَنْ كَانَ فِي الْمَهْدِ صَبِيًّا
30. He said: "I am a servant of God, He has given me the Book and made me a prophet."
٣٠  قَالَ إِنِّي عَبْدُ اللَّهِ آتَانِيَ الْكِتَابَ وَجَعَلَنِي نَبِيًّا
31. "And He has made me blessed wherever I am, and He has charged me with the contact prayer and purification as long as I am alive."
٣١  وَجَعَلَنِي مُبَارَكًا أَيْنَ مَا كُنْتُ وَأَوْصَانِي بِالصَّلَاةِ وَالزَّكَاةِ مَا دُمْتُ حَيًّا
32. "And to be dutiful to my mother, and He has not mademe a mischievous tyrant."
٣٢  وَبَرًّا بِوَالِدَتِي وَلَمْ يَجْعَلْنِي جَبَّارًا شَقِيًّا
33. "And peace be upon me the day I was born, and the day I die, and the Day I am resurrected alive."
٣٣  وَالسَّلَامُ عَلَيَّ يَوْمَ وُلِدْتُ وَيَوْمَ أَمُوتُ وَيَوْمَ أُبْعَثُ حَيًّا
34. Such was Jesus, son of Mary, and this is the truth of the matter in which they doubt.
٣٤  ذَٰلِكَ عِيسَى ابْنُ مَرْيَمَ ۚ قَوْلَ الْحَقِّ الَّذِي فِيهِ يَمْتَرُونَ
35. God was never to take a son, be He glorified. If He decrees a matter, then He simply says to it: 'Be,' and it is.
٣٥  مَا كَانَ لِلَّهِ أَنْ يَتَّخِذَ مِنْ وَلَدٍ ۖ سُبْحَانَهُ ۚ إِذَا قَضَىٰ أَمْرًا فَإِنَّمَا يَقُولُ لَهُ كُنْ فَيَكُونُ
36. And God is my Lord and your Lord, so serve Him. This is a straight path.
٣٦  وَإِنَّ اللَّهَ رَبِّي وَرَبُّكُمْ فَاعْبُدُوهُ ۚ هَٰذَا صِرَاطٌ مُسْتَقِيمٌ
37. Thus the Confederates disputed between them. Therefore, woe to those who have rejected from the scene of a terrible Day.
٣٧  فَاخْتَلَفَ الْأَحْزَابُ مِنْ بَيْنِهِمْ ۖ فَوَيْلٌ لِلَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا مِنْ مَشْهَدِ يَوْمٍ عَظِيمٍ
38. Listen to what they say and watch on the Day they come to Us. But the wicked today are in a clear misguidance.
٣٨  أَسْمِعْ بِهِمْ وَأَبْصِرْ يَوْمَ يَأْتُونَنَا ۖ لَٰكِنِ الظَّالِمُونَ الْيَوْمَ فِي ضَلَالٍ مُبِينٍ
39. And warn them of the Day of Remorse. When the matter is decided while they are oblivious, and they do not believe.
٣٩  وَأَنْذِرْهُمْ يَوْمَ الْحَسْرَةِ إِذْ قُضِيَ الْأَمْرُ وَهُمْ فِي غَفْلَةٍ وَهُمْ لَا يُؤْمِنُونَ
40. It is We who will inherit the earth and all that is on it. And to Us they will return.
٤٠  إِنَّا نَحْنُ نَرِثُ الْأَرْضَ وَمَنْ عَلَيْهَا وَإِلَيْنَا يُرْجَعُونَ
41. And recall in the Book, Abraham; he was a man of truth, a prophet.
٤١  وَاذْكُرْ فِي الْكِتَابِ إِبْرَاهِيمَ ۚ إِنَّهُ كَانَ صِدِّيقًا نَبِيًّا
42. When he said to his father: "O father, why do you serve what does not hear or see, nor help you in anything?"
٤٢  إِذْ قَالَ لِأَبِيهِ يَا أَبَتِ لِمَ تَعْبُدُ مَا لَا يَسْمَعُ وَلَا يُبْصِرُ وَلَا يُغْنِي عَنْكَ شَيْئًا
43. "My father, knowledge has come to me which did not come to you. So follow me that I will guide you to a level path."
٤٣  يَا أَبَتِ إِنِّي قَدْ جَاءَنِي مِنَ الْعِلْمِ مَا لَمْ يَأْتِكَ فَاتَّبِعْنِي أَهْدِكَ صِرَاطًا سَوِيًّا
44. "My father, do not serve the devil. For the devil was ever disobedient to the Almighty."
٤٤  يَا أَبَتِ لَا تَعْبُدِ الشَّيْطَانَ ۖ إِنَّ الشَّيْطَانَ كَانَ لِلرَّحْمَٰنِ عَصِيًّا
45. "My father, I fear that a retribution will inflict you from the Almighty and that you will become an ally to the devil."
٤٥  يَا أَبَتِ إِنِّي أَخَافُ أَنْ يَمَسَّكَ عَذَابٌ مِنَ الرَّحْمَٰنِ فَتَكُونَ لِلشَّيْطَانِ وَلِيًّا
46. He said: "Have you abandoned my gods O Abraham? If you do not stop this, I will stone you; and let me be."
٤٦  قَالَ أَرَاغِبٌ أَنْتَ عَنْ آلِهَتِي يَا إِبْرَاهِيمُ ۖ لَئِنْ لَمْ تَنْتَهِ لَأَرْجُمَنَّكَ ۖ وَاهْجُرْنِي مَلِيًّا
47. He said: "Peace be upon you, I will ask forgiveness for you from my Lord. He has been most kind to me."
٤٧  قَالَ سَلَامٌ عَلَيْكَ ۖ سَأَسْتَغْفِرُ لَكَ رَبِّي ۖ إِنَّهُ كَانَ بِي حَفِيًّا
48. "And I will abandon you and what you call on besides God. And I will implore my Lord, hoping that I will not be mischievous in imploring my Lord."
٤٨  وَأَعْتَزِلُكُمْ وَمَا تَدْعُونَ مِنْ دُونِ اللَّهِ وَأَدْعُو رَبِّي عَسَىٰ أَلَّا أَكُونَ بِدُعَاءِ رَبِّي شَقِيًّا
49. So when he abandoned them and what they served besides God, We granted him Isaac and Jacob, and each of them We made a prophet.
٤٩  فَلَمَّا اعْتَزَلَهُمْ وَمَا يَعْبُدُونَ مِنْ دُونِ اللَّهِ وَهَبْنَا لَهُ إِسْحَاقَ وَيَعْقُوبَ ۖ وَكُلًّا جَعَلْنَا نَبِيًّا
50. And We granted them from Our mercy, and We made for them a tongue of truthfulness to be heard.
٥٠  وَوَهَبْنَا لَهُمْ مِنْ رَحْمَتِنَا وَجَعَلْنَا لَهُمْ لِسَانَ صِدْقٍ عَلِيًّا
51. And recall in the Book, Moses; he was loyal, and he was a messenger prophet.
٥١  وَاذْكُرْ فِي الْكِتَابِ مُوسَىٰ ۚ إِنَّهُ كَانَ مُخْلَصًا وَكَانَ رَسُولًا نَبِيًّا
52. And We called him from the right side of the mount, and We brought him close to talk with.
٥٢  وَنَادَيْنَاهُ مِنْ جَانِبِ الطُّورِ الْأَيْمَنِ وَقَرَّبْنَاهُ نَجِيًّا
53. And We granted him from Our mercy his brother Aaron as a prophet.
٥٣  وَوَهَبْنَا لَهُ مِنْ رَحْمَتِنَا أَخَاهُ هَارُونَ نَبِيًّا
54. And recall in the Book, Ishmael; he was truthful to his promise, and he was a messenger prophet.
٥٤  وَاذْكُرْ فِي الْكِتَابِ إِسْمَاعِيلَ ۚ إِنَّهُ كَانَ صَادِقَ الْوَعْدِ وَكَانَ رَسُولًا نَبِيًّا
55. And he used to instruct his family to the contact prayer and purification, and his Lord was pleased with him.
٥٥  وَكَانَ يَأْمُرُ أَهْلَهُ بِالصَّلَاةِ وَالزَّكَاةِ وَكَانَ عِنْدَ رَبِّهِ مَرْضِيًّا
56. And recall in the Book, Enoch; he was a man of truth, a prophet.
٥٦  وَاذْكُرْ فِي الْكِتَابِ إِدْرِيسَ ۚ إِنَّهُ كَانَ صِدِّيقًا نَبِيًّا
57. And We raised him to a high place.
٥٧  وَرَفَعْنَاهُ مَكَانًا عَلِيًّا
58. Those are the ones whom God has blessed from among the prophets from the progeny of Adam, and those We carried with Noah, and from the progeny of Abraham and Israel, and from whom We have guided and chosen. When the revelations of the Almighty are recited to them, they fall down prostrating, and in tears.
٥٨  أُولَٰئِكَ الَّذِينَ أَنْعَمَ اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِمْ مِنَ النَّبِيِّينَ مِنْ ذُرِّيَّةِ آدَمَ وَمِمَّنْ حَمَلْنَا مَعَ نُوحٍ وَمِنْ ذُرِّيَّةِ إِبْرَاهِيمَ وَإِسْرَائِيلَ وَمِمَّنْ هَدَيْنَا وَاجْتَبَيْنَا ۚ إِذَا تُتْلَىٰ عَلَيْهِمْ آيَاتُ الرَّحْمَٰنِ خَرُّوا سُجَّدًا وَبُكِيًّا ۩
[God is the Greatest]
[الله أكبر]
59. Then, generations came after them who lost the contact prayer, and followed desires. They will find their consequences.
٥٩  فَخَلَفَ مِنْ بَعْدِهِمْ خَلْفٌ أَضَاعُوا الصَّلَاةَ وَاتَّبَعُوا الشَّهَوَاتِ ۖ فَسَوْفَ يَلْقَوْنَ غَيًّا
60. Except for whoever repents and believes and does good works; they will be admitted to the Paradise, and they will not be wronged in the least.
٦٠  إِلَّا مَنْ تَابَ وَآمَنَ وَعَمِلَ صَالِحًا فَأُولَٰئِكَ يَدْخُلُونَ الْجَنَّةَ وَلَا يُظْلَمُونَ شَيْئًا
61. Gardens of delight; that the Almighty had promised His servants in the unseen. His promise must come to pass.
٦١  جَنَّاتِ عَدْنٍ الَّتِي وَعَدَ الرَّحْمَٰنُ عِبَادَهُ بِالْغَيْبِ ۚ إِنَّهُ كَانَ وَعْدُهُ مَأْتِيًّا
62. They will not hear in it any nonsense, only peace. And they will have their provision in it morning and evening.
٦٢  لَا يَسْمَعُونَ فِيهَا لَغْوًا إِلَّا سَلَامًا ۖ وَلَهُمْ رِزْقُهُمْ فِيهَا بُكْرَةً وَعَشِيًّا
63. Such is the Paradise that We inherit to any of Our servants who are righteous.
٦٣  تِلْكَ الْجَنَّةُ الَّتِي نُورِثُ مِنْ عِبَادِنَا مَنْ كَانَ تَقِيًّا
64. "And we are not sent except by the authority of your Lord. To Him are our present and our future, and all that is in-between. And your Lord was never to forget."
٦٤  وَمَا نَتَنَزَّلُ إِلَّا بِأَمْرِ رَبِّكَ ۖ لَهُ مَا بَيْنَ أَيْدِينَا وَمَا خَلْفَنَا وَمَا بَيْنَ ذَٰلِكَ ۚ وَمَا كَانَ رَبُّكَ نَسِيًّا
65. "The Lord of the heavens and the earth and what is between them. So serve Him and be patient in His service. Do you know anything that is like Him?"
٦٥  رَبُّ السَّمَاوَاتِ وَالْأَرْضِ وَمَا بَيْنَهُمَا فَاعْبُدْهُ وَاصْطَبِرْ لِعِبَادَتِهِ ۚ هَلْ تَعْلَمُ لَهُ سَمِيًّا
66. And man says: "Can it be that when I am dead, I will be brought out alive?"
٦٦  وَيَقُولُ الْإِنْسَانُ أَإِذَا مَا مِتُّ لَسَوْفَ أُخْرَجُ حَيًّا
67. Does man not remember that We created him before, when he was not a thing?
٦٧  أَوَلَا يَذْكُرُ الْإِنْسَانُ أَنَّا خَلَقْنَاهُ مِنْ قَبْلُ وَلَمْ يَكُ شَيْئًا
68. By your Lord, We will gather them and the devils, then We will place them around Hell on their knees.
٦٨  فَوَرَبِّكَ لَنَحْشُرَنَّهُمْ وَالشَّيَاطِينَ ثُمَّ لَنُحْضِرَنَّهُمْ حَوْلَ جَهَنَّمَ جِثِيًّا
69. Then We will drag out from every clan the ones which were most in opposition to the Almighty.
٦٩  ثُمَّ لَنَنْزِعَنَّ مِنْ كُلِّ شِيعَةٍ أَيُّهُمْ أَشَدُّ عَلَى الرَّحْمَٰنِ عِتِيًّا
70. Then, it is We who are best aware of those who deserve to be burnt therein.
٧٠  ثُمَّ لَنَحْنُ أَعْلَمُ بِالَّذِينَ هُمْ أَوْلَىٰ بِهَا صِلِيًّا
71. And every single one of you will encounter it. This for your Lord is a certainty that will come to pass.
٧١  وَإِنْ مِنْكُمْ إِلَّا وَارِدُهَا ۚ كَانَ عَلَىٰ رَبِّكَ حَتْمًا مَقْضِيًّا
72. Then We will save those who were righteous, and We will leave the wicked in it on their knees.
٧٢  ثُمَّ نُنَجِّي الَّذِينَ اتَّقَوْا وَنَذَرُ الظَّالِمِينَ فِيهَا جِثِيًّا
73. And when Our clear revelations were recited to them, those who rejected said to those who believed: "Which of our two groups is in a better station and more prosperous?"
٧٣  وَإِذَا تُتْلَىٰ عَلَيْهِمْ آيَاتُنَا بَيِّنَاتٍ قَالَ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا لِلَّذِينَ آمَنُوا أَيُّ الْفَرِيقَيْنِ خَيْرٌ مَقَامًا وَأَحْسَنُ نَدِيًّا
74. And how many a generation have We destroyed before them? They had more wealth and more influence.
٧٤  وَكَمْ أَهْلَكْنَا قَبْلَهُمْ مِنْ قَرْنٍ هُمْ أَحْسَنُ أَثَاثًا وَرِئْيًا
75. Say: "Whoever is in misguidance, then the Almighty will lead them on." Until they see what they have been promised, either the retribution or the Hour. Then they will know who is in a worse place and weaker in power.
٧٥  قُلْ مَنْ كَانَ فِي الضَّلَالَةِ فَلْيَمْدُدْ لَهُ الرَّحْمَٰنُ مَدًّا ۚ حَتَّىٰ إِذَا رَأَوْا مَا يُوعَدُونَ إِمَّا الْعَذَابَ وَإِمَّا السَّاعَةَ فَسَيَعْلَمُونَ مَنْ هُوَ شَرٌّ مَكَانًا وَأَضْعَفُ جُنْدًا
76. And God increases the guidance of those who are guided. And the goodness that endures is better with your Lord as a reward and a far better return.
٧٦  وَيَزِيدُ اللَّهُ الَّذِينَ اهْتَدَوْا هُدًى ۗ وَالْبَاقِيَاتُ الصَّالِحَاتُ خَيْرٌ عِنْدَ رَبِّكَ ثَوَابًا وَخَيْرٌ مَرَدًّا
77. Did you see the one who rejected Our revelations and said: "I will be given wealth and children."
٧٧  أَفَرَأَيْتَ الَّذِي كَفَرَ بِآيَاتِنَا وَقَالَ لَأُوتَيَنَّ مَالًا وَوَلَدًا
78. Did he look into the future? Or has he taken a pledge with the Almighty?
٧٨  أَطَّلَعَ الْغَيْبَ أَمِ اتَّخَذَ عِنْدَ الرَّحْمَٰنِ عَهْدًا
79. No, We will record what he says, and We will increase for him the retribution significantly.
٧٩  كَلَّا ۚ سَنَكْتُبُ مَا يَقُولُ وَنَمُدُّ لَهُ مِنَ الْعَذَابِ مَدًّا
80. Then We inherit from him all that he said, and he shall come to Us all alone.
٨٠  وَنَرِثُهُ مَا يَقُولُ وَيَأْتِينَا فَرْدًا
81. And they have taken gods besides God to be for them their glory.
٨١  وَاتَّخَذُوا مِنْ دُونِ اللَّهِ آلِهَةً لِيَكُونُوا لَهُمْ عِزًّا
82. On the contrary, they will reject their service of them and they will be standing against them.
٨٢  كَلَّا ۚ سَيَكْفُرُونَ بِعِبَادَتِهِمْ وَيَكُونُونَ عَلَيْهِمْ ضِدًّا
83. Did you not see that We send the devils upon the rejecters to push them with incitement?
٨٣  أَلَمْ تَرَ أَنَّا أَرْسَلْنَا الشَّيَاطِينَ عَلَى الْكَافِرِينَ تَؤُزُّهُمْ أَزًّا
84. So do not be in haste towards them; We are preparing for them a preparation.
٨٤  فَلَا تَعْجَلْ عَلَيْهِمْ ۖ إِنَّمَا نَعُدُّ لَهُمْ عَدًّا
85. The Day We gather the righteous to the Almighty as a delegation.
٨٥  يَوْمَ نَحْشُرُ الْمُتَّقِينَ إِلَى الرَّحْمَٰنِ وَفْدًا
86. And We drive the criminals to Hell as a herd.
٨٦  وَنَسُوقُ الْمُجْرِمِينَ إِلَىٰ جَهَنَّمَ وِرْدًا
87. None will possess intercession, except for he who has taken a pledge with the Almighty.
٨٧  لَا يَمْلِكُونَ الشَّفَاعَةَ إِلَّا مَنِ اتَّخَذَ عِنْدَ الرَّحْمَٰنِ عَهْدًا
88. And they said the Almighty has taken a son!
٨٨  وَقَالُوا اتَّخَذَ الرَّحْمَٰنُ وَلَدًا
89. You have come with a gross blasphemy.
٨٩  لَقَدْ جِئْتُمْ شَيْئًا إِدًّا
90. The heavens are about to shatter from it, and the earth crack open, and the mountains fall and crumble.
٩٠  تَكَادُ السَّمَاوَاتُ يَتَفَطَّرْنَ مِنْهُ وَتَنْشَقُّ الْأَرْضُ وَتَخِرُّ الْجِبَالُ هَدًّا
91. That they claimed that the Almighty had a son!
٩١  أَنْ دَعَوْا لِلرَّحْمَٰنِ وَلَدًا
92. And what need does the Almighty have to take a son?
٩٢  وَمَا يَنْبَغِي لِلرَّحْمَٰنِ أَنْ يَتَّخِذَ وَلَدًا
93. When all there is in the heavens and the earth will come to the Almighty as servants.
٩٣  إِنْ كُلُّ مَنْ فِي السَّمَاوَاتِ وَالْأَرْضِ إِلَّا آتِي الرَّحْمَٰنِ عَبْدًا
94. He has encompassed them, and counted them one by one.
٩٤  لَقَدْ أَحْصَاهُمْ وَعَدَّهُمْ عَدًّا
95. And all of them will come to Him on the Day of Resurrection, all alone.
٩٥  وَكُلُّهُمْ آتِيهِ يَوْمَ الْقِيَامَةِ فَرْدًا
96. Those who believe and do good works, the Almighty will make for them affection.
٩٦  إِنَّ الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا وَعَمِلُوا الصَّالِحَاتِ سَيَجْعَلُ لَهُمُ الرَّحْمَٰنُ وُدًّا
97. Thus We have made this easy in your tongue so that you may give good news with it to the righteous and that you may warn with it the quarrelsome people.
٩٧  فَإِنَّمَا يَسَّرْنَاهُ بِلِسَانِكَ لِتُبَشِّرَ بِهِ الْمُتَّقِينَ وَتُنْذِرَ بِهِ قَوْمًا لُدًّا
98. And how many a generation have We destroyed before them? Do you perceive any of them or hear from them a sound?
٩٨  وَكَمْ أَهْلَكْنَا قَبْلَهُمْ مِنْ قَرْنٍ هَلْ تُحِسُّ مِنْهُمْ مِنْ أَحَدٍ أَوْ تَسْمَعُ لَهُمْ رِكْزًا
[God is the Greatest]
[الله أكبر]